<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Spatial Thoughts</title><link href="http://www.spatialthoughts.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.spatialthoughts.com/feeds/conference.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.spatialthoughts.com/</id><updated>2016-11-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>OpenAQ Workshop Notes</title><link href="http://www.spatialthoughts.com/blog/conference/openaq-workshop-notes/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-25T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-11-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Ujaval Gandhi</name></author><id>tag:www.spatialthoughts.com,2016-11-25:blog/conference/openaq-workshop-notes/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently attended the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://medium.com/&amp;#64;openaq/the-next-openaq-workshop-is-in-delhi-apply-to-come-7622aa60e48e#.e8xvdj3rw"&gt;OpenAQ workshop&lt;/a&gt;  in Delhi . The workshop’s goal was to bring tech, science and media folks working on air quality together and brainstorm how to use open data to tackle air pollution challenges. Below are my notes and links to materials presented during the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are my notes and links to materials presented during the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="openaq"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;OpenAQ&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://openaq.org/"&gt;OpenAQ&lt;/a&gt; is a platform and community that aggregates and shares open air quality data from around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAQ was co-founded by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/christahasenkopfa"&gt;Christa Hasenkopf&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/joeflasher"&gt;Joe Flasher&lt;/a&gt;. Christa works full time on OpenAQ and Joe works part-time as the lead developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="notes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="day-1-november-24-2016"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Day 1 - November 24, 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id2"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/0dhwd9jhng18lmj/1_Welcome.pptx?dl=0"&gt;Welcome, Workshop Goals,  Group Introductions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Folks at my table&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/varun_jhaveri"&gt;Varun Jhaveri:&lt;/a&gt; (IIC, University of Chicago)  Worked on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.timeout.com/chicago/blog/chicago-has-started-installing-sensors-that-will-monitor-the-city-082916"&gt;Chicago Sensor network&lt;/a&gt;. On a project to install a similar network in Delhi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/shijith"&gt;Shijith&lt;/a&gt;: Data Journalist at WION news. Interested in using open data to report on aur quality issues in Delhi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://in.linkedin.com/in/gangadharsulkunte"&gt;Gangadhar Sulkunte&lt;/a&gt;: Entrepreneur interested in DIY sensors. Launched a helium balloon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.urbanemissions.info/about"&gt;Nishad KA&lt;/a&gt; : Research Associate at Urban Emissions. GIS-guy. Currently working on mapping of brick kilns to quantify their effect on air pollution. Uses Google Earth imagery to locate brick kilns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://in.linkedin.com/in/jaykannaiyan"&gt;Jay Kannaiyan&lt;/a&gt;: Found of Smart Air Filters. Low cost DIY air purifiers. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://overdrive.in/features/jay-kannaiyans-ride-around-the-world-on-a-motorcycle/"&gt;Rode his motorcycle around the world&lt;/a&gt;  for 3 years!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.edf.org/people/richie-ahuja"&gt;Richie Ahuja&lt;/a&gt;: India director at Environmental Defence Fund. Interested in community engagement around air quality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/named_none"&gt;Ayush Goel&lt;/a&gt;: iOS developer and open data enthusiast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id3"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/d2k5qripf9dp61j/2_IntroducingOpenAQ_Delhi2016.pptx?dl=0"&gt;Introducing the OpenAQ Platform + Community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speakers: Christa Hasenkopf and Joe Flasher, OpenAQ  - 30 minutes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAQ tagline: Fighting Air Inequality&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slide 4: Air Quality vs. GDP. Outliers are Qatar Bahrain UAE (high GDP - high pollution)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slide 5: Research gap: Top 10 most polluted cities have published &amp;lt;40 papers (I didn’t quite agree with the premise that more research results in better air quality)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;aqicn.org is the top aggregator. But can’t download data or programmatic access to historical data. That’s why openaq was started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id4"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/rw58c631o828cqm/4_Guttikunda%20-%20OpenAQ.pptx?dl=0"&gt;Air Quality Landscape in Delhi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaker: Sarath Guttikunda, Urban Emissions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Need for more Epidemiology Studies to drive policy change. Health impact of air pollution at higher levels is not well understood.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.phfi.org/"&gt;Public Health Foundation of India (PHFI)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sriramachandra.edu.in/university/research.php?did=41"&gt;Sri Ramachandra University&lt;/a&gt; leading studies in India on impact of air pollution on health&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 target audiences for AQ data. These 2 should never be mixed and always addressed separately&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science &amp;amp; Policy - numbers, coverage of pollutants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Public Awareness - Air quality index, healthy/unhealthy - lose severity from science perspective&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 550 manual pollution measuring stations in India. They are manually measured and entered. Someone goes in daily, changes the filter, weights it and enters data manually. Large delay in publishing data - challenge for Journalists and reporting on old data is hard. Noone wants to know what happened a month ago. That’s why lack of media stories for cities other than Delhi even though the pollution levels are as bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;60 stations are continuous monitoring stations and publishing real time data on CPCB website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sensors costs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CPCB sensors costs ~ Rs 1 Crore (USD 150k). Measures all pollutants. Includes daily maintenance etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;US embassy sensors costs ~ Rs. 10 Lakh (USD 15k) but measures only PM2.5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low cost sensors range from Rs. 10k - 40k (USD 200 - 800) - measures only PM2.5 and PM10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has there been any concrete policy change based on more data?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Urban Emissions &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.urbanemissions.info/emissions-india-coal-fired-power-plants/"&gt;published a report&lt;/a&gt; on health impact of coal power plants and lag in standards. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=133726"&gt;New stricter regulations&lt;/a&gt; were adopted based on this report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="india-air-quality"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;India Air Quality&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pallavi Pant, University of Mass - Amherst&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Runs the India Air Quality blog at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://indiaaq.wordpress.com/"&gt;https://indiaaq.wordpress.com/&lt;/a&gt; and tweets at &amp;#64;airqualityindia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="air-quality-in-rwanda"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Air Quality in Rwanda&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Langley Dewitt, MIT, Kigali&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measure air quality in Rwanda using bike-taxi drivers carrying sensors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="lunch"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Lunch&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Met Barun Aggarwal from Breathe Easy who makes air purifiers. Person behind the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.business-standard.com/article/beyond-business/inside-new-delhi-s-healthiest-building-115121101134_1.html"&gt;Healthiest Building in India&lt;/a&gt; - Paharpur Business Centre. Barun also runs &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.careforair.org/"&gt;Care for Air&lt;/a&gt; non-profit that was a partner for this workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are some good low-cost air quality sensors one can buy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://originstech.com/products/laser-egg/"&gt;Laser Egg monitor&lt;/a&gt; is the most popular. Namita (who was in the workshop) from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.airveda.com/"&gt;Airveda&lt;/a&gt; produces one at Rs. 10k. Calibration is a challenge as it drifts over time. Their sensors have the ability to receive OTA calibration updates to account for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="building-on-top-of-open-data"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Building on Top of - Open Data&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speakers: Joe Flasher, OpenAQ - 30 minutes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAQ system architecture. Runs on Amazon CLoud&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big fan of Lambda functions. Reduces sysadmin work as no servers to be managed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Openaq-fetch&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Openaq-api&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After fetch, kick of aggregations and stored in elasticache&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Postgres data - 30M records&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daily CSV dump on S3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="ropenaq"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;ROpenAQ&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maelle Salmon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R package for openaq&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id5"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/xpr5yvcd961g57q/8_Amrit_Smokey-OpenAQ-Presentation.pdf?dl=0"&gt;Smokey - The Air Quality Chatbot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amrit Sharma&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chatbot for FB, Twitter. Based on OpenAQ API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="day-2-november-25-2016"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Day 2 - November 25, 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="indian-open-data-association"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Indian Open Data Association&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mrutyunjay Mishra (M2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open Sandbox model - give open access to data and let developers play with it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://openenvironment.indiaopendata.com/#/dashboard/"&gt;Open Environment Data Project&lt;/a&gt; is a plotform to collect and disseminate open air quality data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have developed a affordable Do-it-Yourself (DiY) personal air quality (Dust SPM 2.5 &amp;amp; 10 micron) monitoring device called &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://openenvironment.indiaopendata.com/#/airowl/"&gt;AirOwl&lt;/a&gt;  - open hardware and software&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also have an outdoor monitor called &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://knowledge.indiaopendata.com/index.php/India_Open_Environment_Data_Project#a.29_Environment_Monitoring_Kits"&gt;EMK&lt;/a&gt; which is aimed at replacing science-grade robust sensors. Brings down the cost from Rs 6 Cr (1M) to Rs. 3 Lakh (USD 50K). Deployed and tested at MIT-run &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.kumbha.org/"&gt;Kumbhathon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="reporting-on-air-quality-at-hindustan-times"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Reporting on Air Quality at Hindustan Times&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ravi Suhag and Piyush Aggarwal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting in context: we breathe 11000 littres (3000 gallons) of air per day&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developed air quality portal at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://airquality.hindustantimes.com/"&gt;http://airquality.hindustantimes.com/&lt;/a&gt; using data from CPCB (Central Pollution Control Board) and IndiaSpend (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://breathe.indiaspend.org/"&gt;http://breathe.indiaspend.org/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty map visualization and historic data. Storytelling using data &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.hindustantimes.com/static/pollution-india-five-charts"&gt;http://www.hindustantimes.com/static/pollution-india-five-charts&lt;/a&gt;
Developed their own scrapers and database since OpenAQ did not have historic data going back 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id7"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.careforair.org/"&gt;Care for Air&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jyoti Pande Lavakare and Barun Aggarwal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small un-funded non-profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advocacy in Schools - nudging kids to uses school buses instead of private cars. Why rich kids come in their own cars? So they can start late and reach home early. Disincentivize use of private cars by allowing buses to come in early and  start early. Car pickups need to come in early and go after school buses leave. 80% private car kids started using school buses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awareness in kids by presentations. Everyone loved the quote &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Don’t trust your senses, trust your sensors&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partnered with the organization called &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jodogyan.org/"&gt;Jodo Gyan&lt;/a&gt; that works on alternate Maths education in schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They had filed a petition with supreme court to ban sale of firecrackers whose &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://indianexpress.com/article/india/india-news-india/sc-bans-sale-of-fire-crackers-in-delhi-ncr-4394657/"&gt;verdict&lt;/a&gt; came in as the workshop was in session!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id9"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.airveda.com/"&gt;Airveda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Namita Gupta&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started by a mom who was faced with an asthmatic kid and no solution on how best to deal with air pollution in Delhi. Better data on indoor vs outdoor pollution levels, variations throughout the day and seasons helped her restrict outdoor play-time for her daughter and buy air purifiers that work to improve the air quality. Significant improvement over a year in the health of the child.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developed low-cost sensor as well as outdoor weatherproof sensors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advocacy by putting large air quality display outside Secretariat building in Delhi and at popular locations where politicians visit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id10"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://changetheair.org/"&gt;Hawa Badlo (ChangeTheAir)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nipun Arora&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Media organization working with OpenAQ data. Their mission is  &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Humanizing the Data&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ran many campaigns to raise awareness about air quality. Funded by GAIL (Gas Authority of India Limited)
School have started acknowledging that air quality is a concern. Interest in measuring and improving air quality&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="workshop-materials"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Workshop Materials&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://medium.com/&amp;#64;openaq/delhi-openaq-workshop-info-materials-and-results-2bd74b88bee6#.3g0s0ebab"&gt;Presentations and Videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://medium.com/&amp;#64;openaq/delhi-openaq-unconference-brainstorm-6b9baf61d4aa#.nzehbio86"&gt;Unconference Topics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1W9q_lf68GOxP4ybmfgUcaS3CeDCx7Nm4A4CBI7NDD5E/edit"&gt;Next steps identified by participants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Notes from FOSS4G India - 2012</title><link href="http://www.spatialthoughts.com/blog/conference/foss4g-india-2012/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-29T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2012-10-29T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Ujaval Gandhi</name></author><id>tag:www.spatialthoughts.com,2012-10-29:blog/conference/foss4g-india-2012/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;India’s first FOSS4G - India conference was organized on 25-26 October, 2012 at
Hyderabad. This was a surprisingly low-profile event and there was very little
buzz about it on the internet. I learnt about it just in time to register and
make it to the event. Here I am sharing some notes and impressions. (notes are
mostly from memory, so please excuse if I missed something)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I haven’t been  to other FOSS4G events, but this was unlike any other Geo
conference I have attended.  It was very formal and  government-centric. All
presentations were from government researchers, employees or students.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The penetration of open-source software within government was deeper than I
anticipated and the decision-makers - including the politicians recognize the
benefits of using open technologies. The Chief Guest - Shri V. Aruna Kumar,
MP from Rajahmundry district commented that he realizes that the real cost of
software is not the upfront cost, but the lifetime maintenance cost and
open-source and open-standards can really benefit in the longer run.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keynote’s main message was that we should really focus on delivering
applications that solve real problems. According to the speaker - Shri Anoop
Singh, Special Secretary to AP Government - we have not even begun to realize
the full potential of GIS within governments. For most end-users and decision
makers, the ‘Science’ or 'System' in GIS isn’t important and GIS should
really be about Geographic Information Services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;India is seen largely as a follower in the open source movement and no big
open-source projects have come out of research institutions here. To address
this, International Institute of Information Technology released one of their
projects - LSIViewer as open-source. The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/LSI-IIIT/lsiviewer"&gt;github upload&lt;/a&gt; was done during the
inauguration of the conference by the chief guest!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prof. Venkatesh Raghavan receiving 2012 &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.osgeo.org/solkatz"&gt;Sol Katz award&lt;/a&gt; Prof. Venkatesh Raghavan, Osaka City
University was chosen as the winner of the 2012 Sol Katz ward by OsGeo. The
award was given to him during the conference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Postgrasql + PostGIS, Geoserver and Openlayers seem to be the platform of
choice. Almost all applications I saw were built  using one of these.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ELOGeo portal was shown an example of learning resources available for open
source geo tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is virtually no  open data for India given the strict geo data policy.
But even within the government departments - there is a lot of reluctance in
data sharing. Everyone talked about this problem of data being guarded very
closely and seldom shared. But some forward thinking departments, especially
in Tamil Nadu, have found a way around it by promoting Web Services. They
publish a WMS feed for the datasets. That way other departments can use the
data without really having any ownership of it. This seems to be working
well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ms. Mahalakshmi from National Informatics Center (NIC) in Tamil Nadu
demonstrated some of most interesting internal applications built by them.
They have built web services for different departments and each department
uses these web services for their application. Administrative boundaries,
census data, land use maps, land parcels, police data and planning related
data are some examples which are available via WMS. She also showed a pretty
cool app that BSNL - Chennai uses to identify fault points in their 2G
network. The map is updated in real-time with pings from their different 2G
sites around Chennai.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bhuvan.nrsc.gov.in/bhuvan/"&gt;BHUVAN&lt;/a&gt; - Indian Space Research
Organization’s (ISRO) portal for disseminating geodata has come a long way
since it’s launch a few years back. It’s built completely using open-source
stack and it’s a pretty snappy app. For the first time, a lot of thematic
datasets are available freely to the public via WMS.  They are also making
some medium and low resolution raw/derived data from Indian remote sensing
satellites available for download. The downloads are for personal use only,
but this is a big step forward in India’s data access policy which has been
very restrictive so far.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, some positives and challenges for Open-source software described by
various speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="why-open-source-is-very-attractive-to-governments"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why open source is very attractive to governments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No upfront cost. Don’t have to navigate complicated and time-consuming
approval and procurement process. Easy to get started at low-cost and do a
proof-of-concept.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standards Compliant. Rising awareness within the government of being
standards compliant. Choosing a proprietary solution which is not standards
compliant can cause problems and raise questions from others in future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No vendor lock-in. Can hire another consultant to run or develop services
since all code is available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="challenges-to-wider-open-source-adoption"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Challenges to wider open source adoption&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lack of support. Not many companies providing development and support. Most
applications shown were written and maintained by in-house staff. Big
opportunities for consultants who can provide support for open source tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change aversion: On the desktop, most people are used to proprietary software
from their education or prior work. One example given was reluctance in the
government to switch to Open Office. Free versions of MS Office is easy to
come by and no incentive to learn and adopt open source solution. Using
open-source software in education is a way to increase the adoption.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lack  of Mature solutions: Politicians and administrators felt they had
limited time in their tenure to implement whatever changes they want and show
progress.  There is always the attraction to choose a well known solution and
get the results. The key message was that they feel the open-source software
is mature but there are no mature solutions based on these that the
governments can adopt without much risk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Notes from Carotonama - 2012</title><link href="http://www.spatialthoughts.com/blog/conference/cartonama-2012/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-28T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2012-10-28T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Ujaval Gandhi</name></author><id>tag:www.spatialthoughts.com,2012-10-28:blog/conference/cartonama-2012/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was at #cartonama conference in Bangalore on 23rd September. It was wonderful
to be among geogeeks and see the energy and enthusiasm. Got to see some great
demos and LBS apps from startups in India. Here's a run down from my notes and
bookmarks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Traffic cams in Bangalore: This was probably the coolest demo for me. Love
the simplicity and usefulness. Just open this URL in your smartphone browser
and get real-time feed from the traffic-cam neareast to you from BTIS.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hackday.freecrow.org/trafficam"&gt;http://hackday.freecrow.org/trafficam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thru the Gall: A Layar-based android app to solve the last-mile direcction
problem in India. Bubbles guide you through the narrow-lanes (galli).
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.layar.com/layers/galli/"&gt;http://www.layar.com/layers/galli/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Padma: Search and Browse Indian documentaries through locations of the clips
in the documentaries &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pad.ma/map"&gt;http://pad.ma/map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DelightCircle: LBS app to discover offers and discounts near you. Surprised
at the coverage and partnerships they are able to genrate in the short time.
Powered by MongoDB at the backend.http://delightcircle.com/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commonfloor.com: Google Maps API app for property search. Nicely done and
simple UI and fast lad times. The team talked about challenges and techniques
they use to de-dup the listings and pin the individual listings to the
apartment block. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.commonfloor.com/apartments-for-sale/maps/"&gt;http://www.commonfloor.com/apartments-for-sale/maps/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yahoo: I had forgotten about yahoo as a geo player. But from the talk the
team seems pretty excited about their geo APIs. The Geo APIs are used by many
yahoo properties internally and available to developers too. The API to
extract locations from free-form-text was cool. YQL is a SQL-like query
interface for their API. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://developer.yahoo.com/yql/console/"&gt;http://developer.yahoo.com/yql/console/&lt;/a&gt;,  APIS at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://developer.yahoo.com/geo/"&gt;http://developer.yahoo.com/geo/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NextDrop: Very interesting idea. Most places in India do not have a regular
water supply and people's day revolves around when they are able to collecct
water. They have built a system that alerts subscribers by sms when they can
expect water based on the information from the utility company. Subscribers
pay Rs.10/month to get this data. Their challenge revoled around locating
their customers on a map - both for billing as well as determining which
pipeline will supply them water. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://nextdrop.org"&gt;http://nextdrop.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lokasi: Simple android app that allows you to share your current location by
sms. Reverse-geocoding + location identifier. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.onze.in/"&gt;http://www.onze.in/&lt;/a&gt;  .
collected POIs + street geometry for entire bangalore is about 6 months with
a 10-person team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brief history of map making: Fun talk with lot of pretty and interesting
maps.  No geo conference is complete without a passionate discussion on
projections :)
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.slideshare.net/sumandro/sumandromapping-thecity27032012-12203410"&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/sumandro/sumandromapping-thecity27032012-12203410&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chalo BEST: Bus route planner for Mumbai using OpenTripPlanner and GTFS feed
from BEST. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://trip.chalobest.in/"&gt;http://trip.chalobest.in/&lt;/a&gt; . Challenges in converting messy
spreadsheet data from the agengy in to GTFS feed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geohash: overview of the geohash system. Lots of discussion around what
geohash is good for. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://geohash.org/"&gt;http://geohash.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</summary></entry></feed>